John J. Driscoll Papers 1987.0025
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
John J. Driscoll Papers
1933-1981
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1987.0025
24 Linear Feet
Papers of John J. Driscoll, labor leader in the Connecticut state AFL-CIO. Materials include photographs, framed certificates of appreciation, day books, published material (newspaper and magazine articles, labor literature), and scrapbooks. Also includes some legal papers created by Bridgeport, Connecticut, judge Margaret Connors Driscoll, John's wife.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
The collection was donated by David Driscoll, John and Margaret Driscoll's son, in 2000. All of the materials were previously stored in the Driscolls' Bridgeport, Connecticut, home.
Biography
John Joseph Driscoll was born in 1911 in Waterbury, Connecticut. The son of Irish immigrants, he graduated Phi Beta Kappa in Philosophy from Wesleyan University, from which he also received a masters degree in English and then earned another graduate degree in Philosophy from Brown University. He spent a year at Harvard Law School but left in 1937 to work for 40 cents an hour at the Bristol Company in Waterbury, where he waged a successful union-organizing campaign. He was soon appointed to a full-time position with the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers. He soon moved on to the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), the United Auto Workers and the newly merged AFL-CIO.
Mr. Driscoll became executive secretary of the Connecticut State Labor Council in 1957 and was elected president in 1961, a position he held until his retirement in 1985. During that time he worked for the rights of public employees to unionize, served on the Governor's Council of Economic Advisors and on the state's first Commission for Higher Education. He was a delegate to five Democratic National Conventions.
Mr. Driscoll was married to Margaret Connors and had a son, David. He lived in Bridgeport when he died on July 21, 1994, at the age of 82.
Margaret Connors Driscoll was born in Bridgeport, Connecticut, likely in 1915, and graduated in 1935 from Wellesley College. She received her law degree from Yale Law School in 1938, one of five women in the class.
Mrs. Driscoll was heavily involved in Democratic politics and labor issues before her appointment as a judge to the Connecticut Juvenile Court in 1960. She served as chief judge -- the first woman to do so -- from 1976 to 1978. She was a judge of the Connecticut Superior Court from 1978 to 1985.
Mrs. Driscoll died on May 15, 2000, in Fairfield, Connecticut, at the age of 85.
Scope and Content Note
Many of the Papers of John Driscoll include files from Margaret Connors Driscoll's career. The Papers consist of correspondence, newspaper clippings, fliers, notes, publications, administrative records, photographs on topics including labor studies and education, unfair labor practices, worker's compensation, CIO annual convention, unemployment compensation, various companies contract negotiations, disabilities insurance, special sessions of General Assembly, the legislative session, mine and mill damage suits, Associations of Catholic Trade Unionists, farm workers, the Workmen's Compensation Act, the Connecticut Conference on Social and Labor Legislation, Award: John Driscoll elected to represent Waterbury Brass Workers Union No. 251, International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelters Workers Executive Board Minutes 1939, Nonferrous Metals Industry Unionism, 1958 Legislature Unemployment Compensation, Present Economic Trends in Connecticut 1958, United Auto Workers (UAW), Legislation in CIO, Legislative Reports and Bulletins, Margaret Driscoll becomes Connecticut's First Female Judge, Various Court Cases Margaret Driscoll as Attorney,
Illustrations (layout features).; Clippings (information artifacts); Notes; Financial Records; Labor leaders; Correspondence; Administrative records; Publications (documents); AFL-CIO. Connecticut State Labor Council
- Series I: Inventory, 1933-1981
  - 1947-1958 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings, Transcripts, Manuscripts, Fliers, Notes, Publications, Administrative Records [Subjects include: Abolishment of Wage Differentials Based on Sex, Derby Gas and Electrical, Local 404, Pleadings, Labor Agreements.]
  - 1933-1981 (Box 2)
    Newspaper Clippings, Photographs, Correspondence, Notes, Administrative and Financial Records [Subjects include: Labor Studies and Education, Unfair Labor Practices, Worker's Compensation.]
  - 1945-1956 (Box 3)
    Illustrations, Notes, Publications, Correspondence, Newspaper Clippings, Fliers, Administrative Records [Subjects include: Labor Proposals, Labor Relations.]
  - 1949-1957 (Box 4)
    Notes, Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, Publications, Administrative and Financial Records [Subjects include: CIO Annual Convention, Unemployment Compensation, Torrington Company Contract Negotiations, Disabilities Insurance, Special Session of General Assembly, Legislative Session.]
  - 1944-1960 (Box 5)
    Notes, Publications, Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, Administrative and Financial Records [Subjects include: Mine-Mill damage suits, Ansonia Brass Workers, Domestic Campaign issues, Associations of Catholic Trade Unionists, Appointment as Judge, Farm Workers, Admission to the Supreme Court of the U.S., Women's conference on Legislative issues, Workmen's Compensation Act.]
  - 1945-1959 (Box 6)
    Notes, Publications, Newspaper Clippings, Correspondence, Administrative Records [Subjects include: Worker's Defense League, International Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers vs. American Brass, Workmen's Compensation Draft Bill.]
- Series II: 2000 Addition, 1928-1994; 11.7 Linear Feet
  - Correspondence, Publications, Photographs, Fliers (pamphlets), Clippings, Notes, Administrative Records, 1928-1994; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_1)
    Scope and Content Note
    Subjects Include: Local 251-International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, Constitution of Local 251, Laborer's Non-Partisan League, Wagner Act, UAW Pension Information, Union Correspondence, Representative of Union Card and Membership Card, Weekly Reports of the Union 1941 by John J. Driscoll, 55th and 56th Annual Convention of the Connecticut Federation of Labor Official Proceedings, Statement by John J. Driscoll President of Connecticut AFL-CIO before the Economic Summit, UAW Memorial Tribute to John J. Driscoll. AFL-CIO: News, Reports, and Union. Margaret Driscoll: News, Articles, and Correspondence
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Legal Documents, Financial Records, Photographs, Notes, 1949-1952; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_2)
    Subjects Include: Correspondence for Various Court Cases for Margaret Driscoll, Workers Compensation Cases against companies such as: Manufacturers Foundry Company, Seymour Manufacturing Company, American Brass Company, Scovill Manufacturing Company and New Haven Copper. Court Cases also include divorce cases and immigration cases. Connecticut State CIO 1952 Official Yearbook, Notebooks of Schedules.
  - Administrative Records, Correspondence, Publications, Clippings, Reproductions of Clippings, Financial Records, Photographs, Fliers (Handouts, Pamphlets), Poster, 1938-1994; 1.3 Linear Feet Folders with labeled tabs. (Box 2000-0056_3)
    Subjects Include: AFL-CIO correspondence, amendments, minutes and conventions. Labor Notes and Votes Newsletter, Constitution of the Connecticut State Labor Council AFL-CIO, 1959. Various awards, memberships and recognitions for John Driscoll. Various 1960's photographs and clippings regarding, strikes, unions, and workers in Connecticut. Professor Robert Asher on Employment Lecture, Radio and Machine Workers of America, Agreement between Westinghouse Electric Corp. and United Electrical, John Driscoll AFL-CIO Election, 1968 Democratic National Convention, The Red Branch Cycle in English Literature, Brochures and Manuals for 1960's Appliances, Checkbooks.
  - Administrative Records, Publications, Clippings, Correspondence, Relia, Photographs, Legal Documents, Fliers (Pamphlets, Handouts), 1938-1970; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_4)
    Subjects Include: Social Action Bulletin, 1970 UAW Proceedings, Binder containing information about the economy that could relate to the AFL-CIO, 1954 and 1955 Connecticut CIO Yearbooks, Authorization forms to Prosecute Wages and Hours, Full Employment Conference, Notebook Agendas, Bishop McAuliffe Memorial Award, By-Laws and Constitutions, Commentary: The Irish Of New York, Union Membership Books, AFL-CIO Newspapers, Connecticut: The Labor Situation, CIO State Council Releases, UAW Administrative Letters, Unemployment Compensation Information, Unemployment Compensation Information, California Unemployment Insurance Act, The Struggle For A Connecticut Steel Mill. Workers Compensation Cases against companies such as: Manufacturers Foundry Company, American Brass Company, Bridgeport Rolling Mills, Mattatuck Manufacturing Company.
  - Publications, Administrative Records, Relia, Clippings, Photographs, Financial Records, Fliers (Handouts, Pamphlets), 1939, 1940, 1942, 1943, 1945, 1979, 1980, 1981, 1989, 1990; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_5)
    Subjects Include: The Union, 100th Anniversary Convention AFL-CIO Pin, International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers AFL-CIO Song Book, AFL-CIO Connecticut State Constitution, Delegate 8th Constitutional Convention Pin, Connecticut State AFL-CIO Legislative Bulletin, Connecticut United Labor Agency, Resolutions to 13th Annual AFL-CIO Convention, AFL-CIO Constitutional Convention Proceedings: 1959, 1961, 1962, 1963. Materials on Progressive Metalworkers Council transfer to UAW. Agenda, Reports, and Resolutions of the Connecticut State Labor Council AFL-CIO: 1962, 1965. Various Union Correspondence and Constitutions, Expense and Insurance Accounts for Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America, Social Action Bulletin, Connecticut Enterprise Zone Study 1947.
  - Photographs, Awards, Clippings, Fliers (Handouts), Correspondence, Publication, 1962-1983; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_6)
    Subjects Include: Photographs (President John F. Kennedy speaking to AFL-CIO leaders, John Driscoll protesting and at work, John Driscoll and Robert A. Petronella). Awards (Member of the Council of Economic Advisors, Diocesan Labor Institute McAuliffe Medal, Recognition for Service in Israel Histadrut Campaign). John Driscoll Retirement, Article on Conglomerate Unions, Re-elect Local Union Officers Flier, Bibliography on Irish and Civil War.
  - Legal Documents, Financial Records, Correspondence, Administrative Records, Publications, Clippings, Fliers (Handouts, Pamphlets), 1945-1955; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_7)
    Subjects Include: Pamphlets about Information for Union Workers. Court Case: The Turner and Seymour Manufacturing Company vs. Torrington Foundry Workers No. 1699. United Office and Professional Workers of America (U.O.P.W.A.) Financial Statements 1948. Court Case: The Plume and Atwood Manufacturing Co. vs. Waterbury Brass Workers Union Local 1251, UAW-CIO. Court Case: United Office and Professional Workers of America CIO vs. Industrial Insurance Agents Union Local 63. Labor Relations Acts, U.O.P.W.A Litigation, other cases involving U.O.P.W.A.
  - Legal Documents, Correspondence, Notes, Clippings, Publications, Relia, Fliers (Handouts), 1949-1959; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_8)
    Subjects Include: Various Court Cases involving Unions and Emploees' vs. Companies including The Loehmann Chevrolet Co., Plume and Atwood Manufacturing Co. and The Scovill Manufacturing Co. General Assembly Legislative Record Index, Various Outlines of House and Senate Bills. Legislations, Meetings and Court Cases on Leglislative Bills. Unemployment Advisory Commission 1950, Senator William Benton Reports regarding The Soviet Union. Correspondence, Statements, and Publications of Senator William Benton. Publications of Economic Outlook, Congressional Record Vol. 96 No. 134. Relia: 20th UAW Convention Pin.
  - Correspondence, Legal Documents, Publications, Notes, Administrative Records, Fliers (Handouts), Clippings, 1935-1957; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_9)
    Subjects Include: Report of election laws commission 1941, Acts and Reports Concerning Voting, Elections and Nominations, Legislative Bulletin: Connecticut Federation of Labor, Connecticut Labor Department Monthly Bulletin. Information and Statutes on Connecticut Mediation and Arbitration. Legislation for Dentists and Technicians. Housing Laws for Connecticut, New Housing Programs, Connecticut Housing Authority: Review of Connecticut Housing Problem and Methods to Eliminate Shortage. Child Labor Acts, Social Security Changes and Information, Public Employee Rights and Regulations, Consumer Price Index Statistics, Cost of Living Statistics, Collective Bargaining Agreements for various Connecticut Unions, General Assembly Legislative Record 1953, Health Insurance and Connecticut Unions. Court Case: Paul McCann vs. Scovill Manufacturing Company. Plume and Atwood Manufacturing Company Return to Work Agreement.
  - Legal Documents, Correspondence, Fliers (pamphlets), Clippings, Publications, Administrative Records, 1949-1960; 1959; 1.3 Linear Feet Folders with labeled tabs. (Box 2000-0056_10)
    Subjects Include: Proceedings, Reports and Journal of 1959 Connecticut Legislation Session. Connecticut Labor Department Monthly Bulletin, Limitations of State Department: Unemployment Compensation. Policies for Economic Growth, Labor's Economic Review, Economic Trends and Outlook. Connecticut Education Information, Bills and Acts, Labor and Education in 1954, Financing Public Education in the Decade Ahead, Equal Rights Amendment 1959, Influences and Reports of Automation in the Workforce, Connecticut State Employee's Council, Connecticut State Labor Council 1958-1959, AFL-CIO: COPE Keeping In Touch, Political Memo from COPE, Labor Developments Abroad 1958-1959, A Guide to Labor Relations Management, Labor Relations Act 1958, Information and Reports on Housing in Connecticut, The Connecticut Moderate Income Housing Program Newsletter, Preliminary Report to The Temporary State Commission on Housing.
  - Publications, Administrative Records, Correspondence, Legal Documents, 1947-1954; 1.3 Linear Feet (Box 2000-0056_11)
    Subjects Include: Connecticut Labor Department Monthly Bulletin, Report on Placement and Unemployment Insurance, Unemployment Compensation, Appeals Statistics Unemployment Commission. Court Cases: Bridgeport Brass Workers Union vs. Thomas Smith, Local 1251 Waterbury Brass Workers vs. Plume and Atwood Manufacturing Company, Authorization to Prosecute Wages and Hours Claim for Overtime.
  - Correspondence, Administrative Records, Photographs, Fliers(Handouts, Pamphlets), Awards, Publications, Clippings, Legal Documents, 1937-1989; 1.3 Linear Feet Folders with labeled tabs. (Box 2000-0056_12)
    Subjects Include: Connecticut Conference on Social and Labor Legislation, Award: John Driscoll elected to represent Waterbury Brass Workers Union No. 251, International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelters Workers Executive Board Minutes 1939, Nonferrous Metals Industry Unionism, 1958 Legislature Unemployment Compensation, Present Economic Trends in Connecticut 1958, United Auto Workers (UAW), Legislation in CIO, Legislative Reports and Bulletins, Margaret Driscoll becomes Connecticut's First Female Judge, Various Court Cases Margaret Driscoll as Attorney, Annual Digest of State and Federal Labor Legislation 1955-1956, Civil Rights Bulletin 1957, Connecticut State Labor Council, Child Labor Laws 1957, CIO Convention and Legislative 1957, Educational Information 1957.